<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Sameer Segal</title>
 <link href="http://sameersegal.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://sameersegal.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2013-04-15T07:27:40+05:30</updated>
 <id>http://sameersegal.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Sameer Segal</name>
 </author>
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dark Knights &#58; Hackers for Impact</title>
   <link href="http://sameersegal.github.io/posts/Dark-Knights"/>
   <updated>2013-04-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://sameersegal.github.io/posts/Dark-Knights</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/dark-knights/wallpaper_burning_1280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A hero. Not the hero we deserved but the hero we needed. Nothing less than a knight. Shining.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A hero. Not the hero we deserved but the hero we needed. Nothing less than a knight. Shining.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an exciting time to be alive, especially here in India. Everything we know is getting disrupted &amp;ndash; except, of course, for the higher technical education. 75% of all graduates in India are engineers, who after spending at least 60+ hours a week for 2 years to get into engineering, spend 4 years trying to run as far as possible from it. I know this really well because I was one such engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After three boring years of Electrical Engineering at one of India&amp;rsquo;s top colleges, I decided I was not cut out to become an engineer. I was better: I was designed to manage and lead people. But, one does not simply get an MBA without building a resume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consciously decided to apply for a &amp;ldquo;different&amp;rdquo; intership. This was summer of 2008 when Microfinance was really hot. The Microfinance Institution (MFI) was looking for any kind of technology recommendations and I was looking to learn as much about business and processes as possible. What started off as a not-so-pure motive, soon changed my life completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first field visit, I was bursting with ideas and questions: Why can&amp;rsquo;t we be faster? Why can&amp;rsquo;t we do it this way? Why can&amp;rsquo;t we use more technology? My supervisor, a  pragmatic young american, tried to explain the limitations and constraints: limited operating margins, costs of implementing technology, tech savvy and language limitations of field agents, failed technology pilots, but highlighted that he is keen on exploring options provided they have been demonstrated to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inquisitiveness and naivety took me to other teams &amp;ndash; Credit, Operations, Distributions, IT. I kept hearing the same message again and again &amp;ldquo;Technology never works at the BoP&amp;rdquo;. The business would say IT never gets our requirements and the IT team would point out that every 3 months &amp;ldquo;they change their requirements &amp;ndash; how does one build technology then?&amp;rdquo;. This, I would realize over the next five years, is common to all social enterprises: Social Enterprises are constantly tweaking their processes based on products/services, geographies or more simply, experimenting and keeping what works. They avoid implementing technology until an investor pushes them or they reach a breaking point. Due to their limited affordability, most technology vendors provide a scaled down product which barely seems to work with zero support. Users then, over time, improvize and enter data in ways to fool the system into supporting their unique products/services, not realizing that they are compounding the problem: increasing inefficiencies, making their data / reporting virtually unusable. There approach to solving the problem is to throw more people and increase the complexity of the process rather than investing in technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on insights from the field, by the end of my internship, I had devised a solution to deliver simple account information in the field (which would earlier take 15 days) using SMS (texting service). The customers loved it, the field force loved it, the senior management loved it. The MFI implemented this at scale. As an intern, I was over the moon, because I had built something that actually works in the field. (Personally, I was also happy to see all the managers subtly acknowledge that they were wrong).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a millenial, I have constantly heard: &amp;ldquo;Its all about user experience&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Build something you want, however outrageous, people will come&amp;rdquo;, etc. Sitting in Bangalore reading blogs, I was made to believe that in Silicon Valley, the more &amp;ldquo;sexy&amp;rdquo; the interface, the more outrageous the idea, the better &amp;mdash; and everyone will want it. I was made to believe that unless you are building a &amp;ldquo;consumer app&amp;rdquo; which gets at least 1 Million users (regardless of how expensive it is), you aren&amp;rsquo;t doing anything useful in life. I grew up thinking developing technology for enterprises is for losers &amp;ndash; its boring, slow, and it just needs to work; it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be the best. At the beginning of the internship, I thought there was a hierarchy: Consumer Apps, Enterprise Apps and then finally technology for Social Enterprises. The average engineer doesn&amp;rsquo;t even know that the third bucket exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internship clarified the role of technology at the Base of the Pyramid. Technology need not always be a premium. By using paper, more people we can find a short term fix, however, with every such decision we are losing an opportunity to provide a better service and more options to the end customer. Most social enterprises pick &amp;ldquo;vanilla&amp;rdquo; products &amp;mdash; products for the largest common denominator. The end customer&amp;rsquo;s needs are built around the constraints and dreams where occupation, family and health history, hyper-local geographic factors, among others play a big role. How can a social enterprise serve customers across even a state in India with about 10 product/service variations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social Enterprises don&amp;rsquo;t have any worthy data that they can mine &amp;mdash; too old (from one-off surveys) or too limited to draw any conclusions. Even if the social enteprise creates an innovative product (e.g. insurance), how does it deliver this through its field force: how does it explain to its field agent to in turn explain to the end customer? Product/service information takes time to percolate downward and as with any wave, it loses energy as it travels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where technology can be game changing and essential today. Technology can help the enterprise work across a larger geography and provide innovative products specifically designed for a sub-population with the same field force. You can provide essential products likes loans in less than two days with a more rigorous credit check. You can repair solar lighting solutions within 24 hours. You can explain complex products like insurance, pension or important topics like solar energy vs kerosene through multimedia content. You can make today&amp;rsquo;s transaction focused microfinance into private banking for the poor, You can provide a youtube like channel on health education &amp;hellip; You can provide options to the base of the pyramid, affordably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sector has had its fair share of disappointing technology implementations, which has limited the utilization of technology to only a few visionary and large enterprises. Additionally, due to the limited affordability and a &amp;ldquo;lack of a market&amp;rdquo; technology vendors don&amp;rsquo;t want to invest too &amp;ldquo;much energy&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; they scale down existing solutions. A Core Banking System with no accounting module is not one feature less. It means the enterprise needs to re-enter data into a separate accounting system, which means slower and inaccurate financial reporting, which means lesser controls, higher risk and therefore less likely to get money and finally less likely to innvoate in products with variably term or repayment schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost three years ago, when we started Artoo, we wanted to create technology that works in the field, technology that is designed specifically for Social Enterprises, technology that is enabling and inviting even for a user with no formal computer education. We wanted Social Enteprises to be treated as a mainstream, marketable sector. These have been three challenging years for us. It has been hard to find engineers who want to &amp;ldquo;code&amp;rdquo; and not work for a Google but for this sector. It has been hard to find social enterprises who are willing to take a leap of faith in doing pilots. It has been hard to pay market rate salaries and offer technology at cost without raising any external capital. We have persevered and survived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have often been slighted by investors and network organizations who draw an imaginary line and call us &amp;ldquo;service providers&amp;rdquo;. Service providers do not fit anyone&amp;rsquo;s mandate: Their impact is derivative, they are &amp;ldquo;merely&amp;rdquo; optimizing the real organization. Technology is not a premium, if implemented correctly, it can be an amplifier of impact. It is time the sector wakes up and invests in creating an ecosystem for technology for impact. It is time, we show the &amp;ldquo;lost&amp;rdquo; engineers, how you can hack for impact!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://my.spill.com/profiles/blogs/nolans-batman-vs-burtons&quot;&gt;my.spill.com&lt;/a&gt;
Five years later, we at Artoo, have developed a more holistic solution. We believe this can dramatically alter the social enterprise landscape. We can help enterprises reach out to a larger cusotmer base. We can help the enterprise offer innovative and customized products rather than providing a product for the largest common denominator. This has the potential to improve the relation between customers and field agents &amp;mdash; moving it from transactional to a consultative one. Isn&amp;rsquo;t that going to be game changing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet in our 3 years as a company,  If we are so non-essential or we can easily be substituted, why haven&amp;rsquo;t social enterprises scaled&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love competition and market driven approach, but there is no point in creating competing models in the same geogrphay to serve the same clients when there are so many places / people untapped. Keeping egos aside and &amp;ldquo;founderitis&amp;rdquo;, I would rather improve what already exits before creating a paraller system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a strong interest in the terms &amp;ldquo;Social Enterprise&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Impact&amp;rdquo;. There are conferences and programs identifying, showcasing and building capacity for social entepreneuers and there conferences that explain the &amp;ldquo;market-driven approach to development&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a even bigger trend of &amp;ldquo;Enterpreneurship&amp;rdquo;. Everyone wants to &amp;ldquo;start up&amp;rdquo;! There is some overlap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Service Provider
Game Changing
Causing a Catch22 for the sector
Optimizing what we have &amp;mdash; a lot of our relearning what others have learnt and cracked&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>