<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Sameer Segal</title>
 <link href="http://sameersegal.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://sameersegal.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2013-04-13T00:45:29+05:30</updated>
 <id>http://sameersegal.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Sameer Segal</name>
 </author>
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dark Knights - Hackers for Impact</title>
   <link href="http://sameersegal.github.io/posts/Dark-Knights"/>
   <updated>2013-04-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://sameersegal.github.io/posts/Dark-Knights</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is an exciting time to be alive, especially here in India. Everything we know is getting disrupted &amp;ndash; except, of course, for the higher technical education. 75% of all graduates in India are engineers, who after spending at least 60+ hours a week for 2 years to get into engineering, spend 4 years trying to run as far as possible from it. I know this really well because I was one such engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After three boring years of Electrical Engineering at one of India&amp;rsquo;s top colleges, I decided I was not cut out to become an engineer. I was better: I was designed to manage and lead people. But, one does not simply get an MBA without building a resume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consciously decided to apply for a &amp;ldquo;different&amp;rdquo; intership. This was summer of 2008 when Microfinance was really hot. The Microfinance Institution (MFI) was looking for any kind of technology recommendations and I was looking to learn as much about business and processes as possible. What started off as a not-so-pure motive, soon changed my life completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first field visit, I was bursting with ideas and questions: Why can&amp;rsquo;t we be faster? Why can&amp;rsquo;t we do it this way? Why can&amp;rsquo;t we use more technology? My supervisor, a young pragmatic american, tried to explain the limitations and constraint: limited operating margins, costs of implementing technology, tech savvy and language limitations of field agents, failed technology pilots, but highlighted that he is keen on exploring options provided they have been demonstrated to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inquisitiveness and naivety took me to other teams &amp;ndash; Credit, Operations, Distributions, IT. I kept hearing the same message again and again &amp;ldquo;Technology never works at the BoP&amp;rdquo;. The business would say IT never gets our requirements and the IT team would point out that every 3 months &amp;ldquo;they change their requirements &amp;ndash; how does one build technology then?&amp;rdquo;. This, I would realize over the next five years, is common to all social enterprises: Social Enterprises are constantly tweaking their processes based on products/services, geographies or more simply, experimenting and keeping what works. They avoid implementing technology until an investor pushes them or they reaching a breaking point. Due to their limited affordability, most technology vendors provide a scaled down product which barely seems to work with zero support. Users, would over time, improvize and enter data in ways to fool the system into supporting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a strong interest in the terms &amp;ldquo;Social Enterprise&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Impact&amp;rdquo;. There are conferences and programs identifying, showcasing and building capacity for social entepreneuers and there conferences that explain the &amp;ldquo;market-driven approach to development&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a even bigger trend of &amp;ldquo;Enterpreneurship&amp;rdquo;. Everyone wants to &amp;ldquo;start up&amp;rdquo;! There is some overlap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Embed Dark Knight Picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are the heroes we need right now, not the ones we deserve. They are the Dark Knights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Service Provider
Game Changing
Causing a Catch22 for the sector
Optimizing what we have &amp;mdash; a lot of our relearning what others have learnt and cracked&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>